Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Information Center Records, 1890s-1987
J. Walter Thompson Company. Information Center records 1890s-1987
J. Walter Thompson Company.
19.5 Linear Feet circa 9,500 Items
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access to some portions of the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives is restricted. For further information, consult a reference archivist.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Information Center Records were transferred to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from the J. Walter Thompson Company in 1987.
Historical Note
The Information Center was founded by the J. Walter Thompson Company New York Office in 1918. The records contain several folders detailing efforts to reorganize and expand the Center's services in the mid-1950s. Included are reports describing the purpose of the Center personnel recruitment efforts, and readings about ways to organize office files. In 1980, some of these records were transferred to the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives, which was established in New York in 1979. Some of the files remained active in the Archives until the records were transferred to Duke University in 1987.
Collection Overview
The Information Center Records span the years from the 1890s to 1987 with the bulk dating from the 1940s to 1987. Reports, memoranda, clippings, financial papers, and printed materials that relate to specific J. Walter Thompson Company accounts and offices and to advertising strategies comprise the majority of the collection and are found in the Vertical Files Series and Communications Committee Reports Series. The Information Center Records provide information about a wide variety of J. Walter Thompson accounts, specific details about its operation of domestic and international offices, and an in-depth view of how specific products were evaluated and promoted. The history of the J. Walter Thompson Company, the organization of multinational advertising agencies, and advertising research and marketing are also represented in this collection.
Particularly highlighted in the Vertical Files Series is information about the T-plan and T-square, which documents the foundation upon which the J. Walter Thompson Company sought to market its clients' products. Knowledge about how particular products were studied and marketed are represented by product histories and case studies in the Vertical files Series. Typical information about a product includes its history, government standards, advertising and sales history, advertising investment sales records, packaging and labeling, consumer research, and surveys relating to the product.
Marketing research studies and media research reports are common types of data found in the J. Walter Thompson domestic and international office records. For example, New York office files contain reports titled Advertising to Women and Advertising and Spanish Speaking Americans. The United Kingdom Files contain a report about the interests of children from four to twelve. While records relating to employees are primarily located in the New York Office files, the Chicago Office files include an Employee Attitude Survey (1969) completed by Elrick and Lavidge, a marketing research company. The domestic and international office files referred to above are located in the Vertical Files Series.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
J. Walter Thompson Company
Advertising agencies -- New York (N.Y.).
Advertising campaigns
Advertising -- Management
Advertising -- Research
Marketing research
Advertising -- Brand name products
Advertising agencies -- Canada
Advertising agencies -- Europe
Advertising agencies -- India
Advertising agencies -- South Africa
Advertising agencies -- Great Britain
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Contents of Collection
- Vertical Files, 1890s-1987, undated
  Developed by the J. Walter Thompson Company as general reference files, they remained active until the company records were transferred to Duke University in 1987. Subdivided into three subseries: Accounts, History, and Organization.
  - Accounts, 1912-1987.
    Contains reports, memoranda, case studies, clippings, and financial papers, chiefly redating to specific J. Walter Thompson Company accounts. Case studies can be found either undo the Case studies subsection or within the folder for the particular account, e.g. Scott Paper Company. The amount of material about specific accounts vary. For some, specific information about prizes, contests, and packaging used to promote specific products is included. Testimonial advertising developed to recruit well-known persons to endorse products and volunteer groups, who employed the J. Walter Thompson Company to promote their causes or concerns, are also represented.
    The subseries is subdivided into two categories: General Information and Specific Client Accounts. General Information includes case studies and lists at the beginning, followed by an alphabetical arrangement by topic. Specific Client Accounts are arranged alphabetically by client name or type of account (e.g. volunteer accounts).
    - Accounts: General Information
      - Case Studies:
        - General information, 1925-1960 (Box 1)
        - Encyclopedia of Advertising, 1924-1925
        - Indexes, 1957
        - Kohl, Howard, 1955-1961
        - Partial List of J. Walter Thompson Company Clients, 1920s
          (Clients: Lever Brothers/ Winchester Repeating Arms Company/ Swift & Company/ Andrew Jergens Company/ American Tobacco Company/ Arbuclde Brothers/ Pond's Extract Company/ Irving National Bank/ Libby, McNeil and Libby/ Northam Warren Company/ O'Sullivan Rubber Company/ Aunt Jemima Mills Company/ Julius Kayser & Company/ Tidewater Oil Company/ The Charles William Stores/ Charles W. Breneman & Company/ Odorono Company/ G. Piel Company/ Gruen Watch Manufacturing Company/ Piel Brothers)
        - Coffee, 1912-1961
          (Clients: Yuban/ Arbuclde Brothers/ Maxwell House/ Chase & Sanbom)
        - Fo-W, 1939-1959
          (Clients: Foundation for Commercial Banks/ Institute of Life Insurance/ Mentholatum Company/ New York Central Railroad/ Northeast Airlines/ Owens-Illinois/ Pond's Extract Company/ Jergens Lotion/ Union Central Life Insurance Company/ Woodbury's Facial Soap)
        - Miscellaneous, 1956-1960
      - Lists:
        - 1969-1978
        - Additions and eliminations, 1947-1986
      - Packages and Labels, 1923-1936
        (Clients: Aunt Jemima/ Cream of Wheat/ Quaker/ Dolly Madison Baking Corporation/ William Freihofer Baking Company/ Hathaway Bakeries/ A.C. Krumm & Son Macaroni Company/ Lever Brothers/ Fleischmann's Distilling Corporation/ Arbuckle Brothers/ Good Luck Pie Filling/ Cutex, Warren Company)
      - Packaging, 1928-1957
        (Clients: General Cigar Company/ White Owl Cigars/ Pond's/ Aqua Velva/ Eastman Kodak Company/ Serpasil Elixir/ Good Luck Margarine)
      - Plans:
        - (Including T-Plan), 1974-1983, undated, (2 folders)
        - (Including Plan and Data Record), 1918-1966, (2 folders)
        - (Including Plan and Data Record), 1918-1966, (Folder 1 of 2)
        - (Including T-Square and New Plan and Data), 1941-1973, (Folder 2 of 2) (Box 2)
        - J. Walter Thompson Company Planning Record, 1957-1964
        - English Slide Guide (T-Plan presentation), 1972
        - T-Plan:
          - London Office, 1944-1964
          - Guide to, 1982
      - Prizes, Contests, 1922-1947
        (Clients: Eastman Kodak Company/ Planter's Nut and Chocolate Company/ Lever Brothers/ Chase & Sanborn/ Magic Baking Powder/ Corning Glass Works/ United States Playing Card Company/ A. & M. Karaghensian/ Royal Baking Powder/ Standard Brands/ Penick and Ford)
      - Prizes, Contests, Examples of Contests Run by Clients, 1923-1925
        (Clients: Cream of Wheat Company/ Lux, Lever Brothers/ Royal Baking Powder/ Sun-Maid)
      - Prizes, contests: Fleischmann's Company, 1923-1934
      - Product Naming, 1919-1937:
        (Clients: Woodbury's/ Jergens Company/ Winchester/ Pond's)
      - Resor, Stanley, 1913-1949
        (Clients: Kdvinator/ Nash Motor Company/ Procter and Gamble/ Atbuclde Brothers/ Tide Water Oil Company/ Charles W. Breneman Company/ Penick and Ford)
      - Publications and clippings, miscellaneous, 1931-1984
    - Accounts: Specific Clients
      - American Gas Association, 1955-1984, (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - Eastman Kodak, 1938-1986, (2 folders)
      - Ford Motor Company:
        - 1942-1985, (3 folders)
        - Dealers, 1956-1985
      - French (R. T. French Company), 1968 (Box 4)
      - Indiana Bell Telephone Company, 1966
      - Kraft, 1904-1984
      - Kraft's Miracle Whip Salad Dressing, 1938
      - Kraft product history:
        - Miracle Whip cheese spreads, 1952-1953
        - Liquid dressings, 1957
        - Mayonnaise, 1957
        - Dinner (macaroni and cheese), 1957
        - Sliced natural cheese, 1957
        - Miracle Whip, 1957
        - Cracker Barrel, 1957
        - Deluxe Slices, 1957
        - Cheez Whiz, 1957 (Box 5)
        - Philadelphia Brand Cream Cheese, 1957
        - Cheese spreads, 1957
      - Lever Brothers
        - 1916-1986, (2 folders)
        - Lux: Case history, 1923-1973
        - Lux liquid: Case history, 1952-1956
        - Clippings, 1950-1986
        - Packaging, 1900-1970
      - M-W: 1976-1984:
        (Clients: Mexicana Airlines/ Mink International/ Orkin/ W.F. Young)
      - McDonnell Douglas:
        - 1958-1986
        - Clippings, 1958-1986 (Box 6)
      - Oscar Mayer and Company, 1961-1986
      - President's Council on Youth Opportunity, 1967-1968
      - Quaker Oats Company:
        - 1927-1986
        - Clippings, 1964-1986
      - Reader's Digest:
        - 1955-1984
        - Panels, 1962
      - Scott Paper Company, 1920-1986, (3 folders)
      - Sears Roebuck and Company, 1961-1973.
      - Testimonial Advertising, 1928-1977 (Box 7)
        (Clients: White Owl Cigars/ Lever Brothers/ Subert House Organ/ Pond 's/ Royal Baking Powder/ Fleischmann's Yeast/ Chase & Sanborn)
      - Trademarks and slogans, 1931-1979
      - United States Marine Corps, 1962-1987, (3 folders)
      - Volunteer, 1959-1985:
        (Clients: Advertising Council/ Alliance to Save Energy/ ADDY Awards/ Bob Hope Heart Research Institute/ Big Apple Circus/ Boy Scouts of America/ Chicago Literacy Council and Charles Levy Circulating Company/ Statue of Liberty, Ellis Island Restoration Project/ United States Food and Drug Administration/ Harbor Festival '79/ Committee for Hand Gun Control/ Los Angdes Zoo/ Help for Retarded Children/ New York Jazz Museum/ Tuskegee Institute/ Salvation Army/ United Cerebral Palsy Association/ United Givers Fund/ United States Savings Bonds/ United Way/ United States Department of Energy)
      - Volunteer:
        - American Red Cross, 1965-1985
        - Citizens Committee to Keep New York City Clean, 1959
        - Save Grand Central Station Committee, 1975-1978
      - Warner Lambert Company, 1962-1990, (2 folders)
  - History, 1934-1987.
    News releases, clippings, memoranda, and printed materials, listing J. Walter Thompson Company advertising campaigns that have won awards. Also includes information about consume pangs, used by the company to provide information about the middle class in the United States which represented the major market for its clients. Some material in the consumer panel folders contains reports from the American Marketing Association meeting in June 1944, which had the theme, Mobilization for Market Expansion. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
    - Awards, 1967-1987, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Consumer Purchase Panel, 1934-1960, (2 folders)
  - Organization, 1890s-1987 (bulk 1940s-1987.)
    Reports, clippings, market studies, media analyses, memoranda, personnel listings, and new business books, relating primarily to specific domestic and international J. Walter Thompson Company offices. The amount of materials about individual offices varies. New York Office Piles comprise the bulk of the subseries. Specifically highlighted are the New York Office's Media and Public Relations Departments; employee training and orientation programs; information about product account representatives; the reorganization of the Information Center; the Grocery Merchandising Committee, which studied the promotion of supermarket products; and data about Review Board procedures and policies. Also information about specific businesses affiliated with the J. Walter Thompson Company such as Brouillard Communications, and Hill and Knowlton.
    The first part of the subseries contains general information about the J. Walter Thompson Company organization and affiliates. The remainder is arranged alphabetically by topic.
    - Organization: General Information
      - 1890s-1980s (Box 8)
      - 1952-1976
      - Lists, 1981-1985
      - A Study of the Reputation of the J. Walter Thompson. Company by Louis Harris and Associates, 1969
      - Affiliates, subsidiaries, and divisions:
        - 1968-1983
        - Brouillard Communications: (Box 9)
          - 1975-1985
          - Communications Watch, 1981-1986
        - Hill and Knowlton, 1970-1986, undated, (2 folders)
        - Hispania, 1980-1986
        - J. Walter Thompson Company:
          - Direct Network, 1978-1985
          - Healthcare, 1968-1986
        - Lord, Geller, Federico and Einstein, 1973-1986
        - Simmons Market Research Bureau, 1967-1985
        - Survival Anglia, 1973
        - Thompson recruitment, 1979-1987
    - Organization: Alphabetical Arrangement
      - Domestic:
        - Atlanta, 1971-1985 (Box 10)
        - Chicago, 1941-1986, (3 folders)
        - Detroit, 1919-1987
        - Los Angeles, 1940-1983
        - Los Angeles, 1965-1985
        - New York Office:
          - Advertising Services Department, 1920-1980
          - Archives, 19841986
          - Art and architecture: Colonial Dining Room, 1921-1982, (2 folders)
          - Broadcasting Department, 1949-1972
          - Communications Forum, 1970-1971
          - Consumer behavior, 1929-1977 (Box 11)
          - Creative Department:
            - 1960-1986, (2 folders)
            - Creative assignments, 1960-1979, (2 folders)
          - Fact books, 1957-1976, (Folders 1-2 of 3)
          - Fact books, 1957-1976, (Folder 3 of 3) (Box 12)
          - Grocery Merchandising Committee, 1954-1957, (2 folders)
            (Clients: Tender Leaf Tea/ Chun King/ Standard Brands/ Royal Nuts/ Fleischmann's Yeast/ United States Brewers Foundation/ Buitoni Foods Corporation/ Sylvania Photolamp Division/ Lever Brothers/ Wool Bureau/ Devoe and Raynolds Paint/ Blue Surf/ Prepared Puddings and Pie Fillings/ Florida Citrus Commission/ Philco Corporation/ Ward Baking Company/ Nationwide Insurance)
          - Industrial and Professional Department, 1949-1965
          - Information Center Records:
            - Miscellaneous, 1916-1976
            - McCarty, Thad B., files:
              - Library director applications and interviews, 1953-1955
              - Competitive ads files, 1954-1955
              - Correspondence, 1953-1955
              - Information Program Reorganization, 1954-1955
              - Information Program Reorganization, 1956, undated
              - J. Walter Thompson Company news excerpts, 1955
              - Organization of information files, 1953-1955, undated
              - Library portfolios: Library report, 1955
              - Review Board notes, 1955
              - Miscellaneous, 1951-1955, undated
          - Media Department:
            - 1956-1986, (3 folders)
            - Media reports, 1965-1974, (5 folders)
              - Prime Time Television Schedule, 1986-1987
            - Media research, 1970-1986, (Folder 1 of 6)
            - Media research, 1970-1986, (Folders 2-6 of 6) (Box 13)
          - Media Department: Media Source Materials and Them to Find Them, 1985
          - Merchandising Department, 1933-1975, (2 folders)
            (Client: Shell Oil Company)
          - Public Relations Department:
            - 1929-1982, (2 folders)
            - Orientation packet, 19661969 (Box 14)
          - Representatives:
            - 1946-1976, (2 folders)
            - Account management assignment, 1944-1987, (4 folders)
          - Review Board, 1916-1972
          - Staff, 1931-1979
          - Training: J. Walter Thompson Company Professional Forum, 1960-1976, (3 folders) (Box 15)
          - Training: J. Walter Thompson Company Professional Forum, 1963-1971
            (Client: Lever Brothers)
          - Training programs, 1960-1984, (2 folders)
        - San Francisco, 1940-1985
      - Finance:
        - 1969-1985
        - Clippings
      - International: General Information
        - 1930-1986, (Folder 1 of 4)
          (Client: S.C. Johnson and Son,; Brite Floor Wax)
        - 1930-1986, (Folders 2-4 of 4) (Box 16)
        - Clippings, 1965-1985
        - Lists, 1937-1985, (2 folders)
        - Press releases: Erskine, and others, 1965
        - Worldwide Public Relations Directory, 1976-1978
        - Worldwide Research Directory, 1976-1977
      - International: Specific Offices:
        - Argentina, 1950-1977
        - Australia, 1947-1984, (1 vol., 2 folders)
        - Austria, 19601979 (Box 17)
        - Belgium, 1974
        - Brazil, 1944-1985, (2 folders)
        - Canada, 1930-1985, (4 folders)
        - France, 1963-1985
          (Clients: Ford Motor Company/ Lefevre-Utile/ Burroughs/ Valstar Beer/ Courtaulds)
        - Germany, 1955-1984, (Folder 1 of 2)
          (Client: Unilever)
        - Germany, 1955-1984, (Folder 2 of 2) (Box 18)
        - India, 1952-1987, (2 folders)
        - Italy, 1966-1984
        - Japan, 1965-1985
        - Latin America, 1968
        - Mexico, 1944-1985
        - Middle East, 1981
        - Netherlands, 1965-1985
        - Peru, 1957-1983
        - South Africa, 1952-1985, (2 folders)
        - Spain, 1967-1985
        - United Kingdom, 1927-1985
          (Clients: Oxo and Fray Bentos/ Oxo cubes and Fray Bentos Conned Beef/ The Wine and Spirit Association of Great Britain/ The Friends of Wine/ The Committee for the Wines of France/ South West African Persian Lamb/ English Electric Refrigerators)
        - United Kingdom, 1948-1977, (3 folders) (Box 19)
          - Clippings, 1962-1987
          - Publications, 1965-1985, (Folders 1-5 of 6)
          - Publications, 1965-1985, (Folder 6 of 6) (Box 20)
      - Staff:
        - Company anniversary list, 1977-1979
        - Directors, officers, vice-presidents, lists, 1955-1986, (2 folders)
- Communications Committee Reports, 1956-1959, undated
  The purpose of the reports was to insure maximum use of studies and projects of a broad general interest throughout the J. Walter Thompson Company offices. Committees were organized in New York, Detroit, Chicago, Los Angdes, and San Francisco in 1957. Each office was responsible for collecting material from its own members and forwarding a list of the Items to the central committee in the New York Office. The reports consist of photo-offset copies and printed material in which such topics as advertising techniques, research, media, industries, and demographics are discussed. Some reports contain excerpts or reprints of articles from external sources. The reports were arbitrarily numbered at some point; they have been arranged in order by these numbers. An information folder filed at the beginning of the series includes statistics about how many times some of the reports circulated to domestic and international offices. Some reports did not have obvious titles. In those cases, the information folder was consulted and the names given for the corresponding numbered report were listed below. Reports 25A and 26 Section I, Part B. are missing.
  - Information folder:
    - No. 1, Copy Testing, 1957 (Box 20)
    - No. 2, Copy Reprints at Low Cost, undated
    - No. 3, Manual of Television Basics, Media Research Department, 1957
    - No. 4, Consumer Product Test Marketing, undated
    - No. 5, Local Rating Service Standards for Lever Brothers Company, 1957
    - No. 6, Magazine Circulation Distribution and Coverage, Media Research Department 1957
    - No. 7, Testing Relative Effectiveness of Sales Propositions, undated
    - No. 8, A Successful Technique for Determining a Brand Image Discussion, n.d
    - No. 9, The Market Promise of a New Product Discussion, undated
    - No. 10, A Technique For Measuring Consumer Attitudes Toward Specific Airline Features, undated
    - No. 11, A Technique In Testing A Copy Theme (Cigarettes), undated
    - No. 12, A Technique To Determine Motivation Underlying Use of a Product, undated
    - No. 13, Well-Known Brand Names Tend To Get Higher Readership Ratings Than They Earn, undated
    - No. 14, A Technique To Determine The Personality. of a Business, undated
    - No. 15, Copy Testing With a Gift Offer (Make-Up Foundation), undated
    - No. 16, A Technique For Determining Consumer Images Of Different Modes of Travel, n.d
    - No. 17, A Measurement of the Effectiveness of Television Advertising, n.d
    - No. 18, Sales Forecasting, 1956, April
    - No. 19, National And Private Brand Competition in Super Market Merchandising, Research Department, 1957, Feb.
    - No. 20, Product Testing, n.d
    - No. 21, J. Walter Thompson--Company Structure, undated
    - No. 22, Copy Testing With a Gift Offer (Picture Tubes), undated
    - No. 23, Report On Newspapers As An Advertising Medium, Media Research Department, 1957, June
    - No. 24, Radio Study No.8--J. Walter Thompson Looks at Radio, Media Research Department, 1957, June
    - No. 25B, The Effectiveness of Repeated Advertisements, Research Department, 1956, June (Box 21)
    - No. 25C, A Study Of Food Advertising Readership, Research Department, 1956, July
    - No. 25D, Standard Brands, Royal Nuts, 1956, Oct.
    - No. 26, Manual of Television Basics, Media Research Department, 1958, Jan., (3 folders)
    - No. 27, How to Increase Acceptability of Display Material To Grocery Chains and Chain Store Operators, undated
    - No. 28, Planning A Local Sales Contest For Ford, 1957, July
    - No. 29, Using the J. Walter Thompson Company Consumer Panel In Sales Promotion Activity, 1957, May 3
    - No. 30, How Many Dollars For Advertising, 1955
    - No. 31, Advertising Budget Requirements 1957and 1958, Media Research Department, 1957, Aug.
    - No. 32, Report On Radio As An Advertising Medium, Media Department, 1957, July
    - No. 33, Ultru Color Demonstration In The J. Walter Thompson Company Television Workshop, undated
    - No. 34, Analysis Of Store Distributed Magazines 1953through 1957, Media Research Department, 1957, Aug.
    - No. 35, Report On Magazines As An Advertising Medium, 1957, Sept.
    - No. 36, The Effectiveness of Industrial Advertising, 1957, Nov.
    - No. 37, A Marketing Profile of the Senior Citizen Group, Research Department, 1957, May
    - No. 38, Use Of Consumer Panel To Measure Influence of a Television Program On a Product's Sales, 1958, May
    - No. 39, Retail Grocery Chain Buying Committee Deliberations, Research Department, 1957, Oct.
    - No. 40, Studying the Over-all Effect of an Advertising Campaign, Research Department, 1957, Sept. (Box 22)